There wasn't a language in the world
that could do what I needed.
>> This is Bjestro, creator of C++, and we
talked about his career starting with
Bell Labs. What gave you the conviction
to fly on your own tab?
>> It was the best place in the world,
right? I mean, do I need anymore?
>> And I also asked him all about
programming language design. What was
the most technically challenging part to
implement? Everybody asks that question
and I think it's a wrong question.
>> But I tend to think that more [music]
abstraction costs you something.
>> It's not the case. We can do negative
overhead abstraction.
>> Is there any part [music] where you
think, "Oh, that that was a mistake.
>> I should have fought harder for that."
>> Here's the full episode. [music]
>> What is the origin story behind C++?
Well, let's start from the real
beginning. I got a job at Bell Labs,
which is a really great place over in
New Jersey. It's not like that anymore,
but at the time it was the best applied
math, applied engineering uh place in
the world. I I looked around, you know,
the great people who were there. They
built Unix, they built C, they did a lot
of uh the theory behind it. And I
realized I had to do something important
otherwise I didn't belong. So uh I
decided I was going to build a
distributed Unix because it was clear
that computers were getting better,
networking was getting better. So we we
we we need some of those one of those.
And uh if I had succeeded it would we
would have had Unix clusters 10 years
earlier or something like that. But of
course I couldn't do it. That's not a
oneperson job. But the first thing I
realized was I there wasn't a language
in the world that could do what I
needed. It needed two things. Low-level
uh access to hardware. So to memory
managers, process uh implementations,
process scheduleuler, network drivers,
uh device drivers, all that kind of
stuff. And then it needed highle things.
It says, well, there's a module here and
this computer and there's a module there
and that computer and uh here's a the
communication protocol they're using and
things like that. And there's lots of
languages that could do either. None
that could do both. The obvious language
for the low-level stuff was C because
well Dennis Richie and Brian Kernan was
down the the hall and [snorts] I said
distributed Unix because I was in the
home where Unix was invented and still
being built.
And for the high level languages there
was a fair number but they were all too
slow and they couldn't manipulate
hardware. But I had uh learned to use
simul. I knew question and yandal that
uh invented object-oriented programming
and similar. And so I decided I had to
merge these two. And the way that was
practical was to take the class concept
from
um from simula and stick it into C so
that it could run much much faster and
be used for systems programming.
And at the same time I made the type
system a bit more regular. user defined
types classes uh was handled the same
way as built-in types and that's
basically the start of what neither
scene nor simul could do which gets us
to generic programming eventually many
years later uh I had to add overloading
I mean we have always had overloading
you can you can add to uh integers you
can add to uh floating point numbers.
You can add a floatingoint number to an
integer with a plus. That's a single uh
uh name, right? And so I had to
generalize that to be able to have
unique set of rules for both built-in
and userdefined types. So that's where
it came from.
>> In one of the lectures that I saw that
you gave, you talked about uh rewriting
a simulator in BCPL. Is that the
distributed Unix work or
>> No, no, that's before that. I went to
Cambridge, England to get a PhD
and uh at some point I decided I needed
a simulator or software on a distributed
system um to to do the the PhD work on
uh distributed systems.
And of course the idea of a distributed
Unix uh three or four years later came
out of the same way of thinking. But um
what I did was I wrote a really nice
simulator in [snorts]
uh Simula. Simula is very good at that.
It's misnamed because it was a general
purpose programming language and it's
having a bad name didn't help it at all.
But anyway, I wrote this simulator and I
wrote little examples, test cases, etc.,
etc. It all worked nicely. Then I tried
the first real run um full scale and I
took the department's uh mainframe and
used it for a very significant time.
and well PhD students can't do that. Um
that's the chemists and the
astrophysicists and such would never
accept it. So I was kicked off the
machine. Uh and it was clear that simul
could write I could write the program in
simul
but I couldn't afford to run it. So I
took the ideas and I moved it to a
little used experimental computer which
was the CAP computer which had hardware
protection and uh capabilities and great
stuff for uh hardware and it was
somewhat unusual. So the astrophysicists
couldn't use it. They they weren't
computer scientists as such but but I
could. And so the only problem was I
couldn't run Simula there because Simul
uh was never ported on that kind of
machine and it was being used on
mainframes and it was proprietary and
everything was wrong in the context of
the cabin computer. So I basically
rewrote my simulator in BCPL
and BCPL is a language that will make C
look like a highle language
and like like it has only one data type
the word
and um it was a very painful exercise
but once I done it my program ran uh I
guesstimated about 50 times faster.
faster
and um I got my data and I got my PhD.
So that was good. But I was convinced I
would never again attempt a problem
with tools that inadequate
as I had uh tried it on the main frame
in uh Cambridge.
And so I I had a list of things that my
ideal language should have and well C++
simul didn't have all of that but it
came closer than any other language that
existed. C++ came out of there.
>> Yeah. In in that lecture you you said
something like that writing that program
in BCPL was so difficult you lost half
your hair debugging. That's um almost
exactly true and I lost the other half
getting C++ going but over the years but
um anyway it worked.
>> You mentioned Bell Labs and I think
there's a lot of curiosity about that
topic just because it's such a legendary
place. when you had graduated um from
your PhD and you were thinking about
where to work socially, what was what
was Bell Labs known as at that time?
Bell Labs was the place to go if you
wanted to do practical engineering
at a large scale at sort of world class
and I think it was easily the best. I
mean, we probably had twice as many
computer scientists as MIT at the time,
things like that. And the computer
science research center had uh great
people
and
some of them had come from um from
Cambridge. Um
and um one day in my last year in
Cambridge uh one of the people from Bill
Labs came along along to give a talk and
give a talk and the uh tradition in
England and in the computer lab is after
um a day's work you go to the pub and
you uh chat with other people to see
what has been going on. And he says,
"Well, when you need a job, give us a
buzz." And so I did. And I
flew over to uh New Jersey on on my own
tab actually. And my later boss, Sandy
Fraser, great guy uh working with
networking,
um told me that I'd come at a wrong
time. They didn't have any jobs.
>> [snorts]
>> This is not what you want to hear when
you've just flown over the Atlantic.
Anyway, the next day I gave a talk um to
a development group, not the research
group, and then they changed their minds
and took me up to the research group and
I worked there for for the next couple
of decades.
>> What was the interview process like?
>> You just talked to some people. I mean
um I I remember having a a longish chat
with Dennis Chief for instance and I I
talked to people doing networking mostly
there there wasn't a
interview process as such uh they hadn't
actually hired anybody new for 5 years
so um no they just did it by the seat of
the pants
>> so it's kind of like the the uh belief
and credibility that other people say
that you have like Dennis Richie talked
to you and that he knew that you knew
what you're talking
>> Sandy Fraser and such they they just uh
talk to you and see what you know and
don't know and uh at the end they they
go to the director and says in this case
we've got a good guy can you give us a
let us let us have him I of course
didn't know anything about that. I
wasn't there. I was out talking to
somebody in California and I get a phone
call from the director and says, "Uh,
would you like to come and work here a
week later?"
What gave you the conviction to fly on
your own tab to go and you there wasn't
even a promise of a job yet?
>> No. Well, it was the best place in the
world, right? I mean, do you need any
more?
it I mean if it worked it was the best
and if it didn't work so what I mean you
can't succeed at everything today
there's more industries has a stronger
pull at that time would it have been IBM
or something that would have been the
best industry
>> I talked to IBM they weren't as good as
the bill labs computer science research
center I was up at Yorktown heights and
I talked to the researchers and I talked
to to the young uh researchers and I
just didn't think they were doing the
right stuff
and and not in the right way and they
were much more controlled and directed
than the uh researchers at Bell Labs.
>> At a place like Bell Labs, how does
project selection go? Like how does how
does all that work once you're employed?
Oh um at the time and I think still
there there are two philosophies about
how to get good research. The one is
that you have a well-designed project uh
chosen carefully by uh management and
higher management uh seriously funded
and maybe you do uh put 20 or 30 people
at the problem and you solve it and you
have something great. [snorts]
Um, the other [clears throat] philosophy
is you hire the best people you can find
and don't tell them what to do. Um, I
mean, my job was described as do
something interesting
in a year's time. Tell us what it you
did
and if we like it, um, we'll extend
we'll give you the same uh, deal next
year. And by the way, um the way you
tell us you write one sheet of paper uh
using more than nine uh nine point font
or or more because you if you can't say
what you did in fairly briefly uh you
probably haven't done something
interesting enough
>> very unusual. So there um they were
actually worrying when they built Unix
because it eventually involved five or
seven people
and it was getting too big for for for
that model of the world of individuals
doing interesting things.
Very different. Uh I would say that on
average this fairly anarchic uh
organization
uh did better than the well organized
thing. Most of the things you've heard
of from Bell Labs uh came out of out
[snorts] of there and then in other part
of the building they were doing hardware
things. So fibers as we use them today
uh came out of there. A lot of the
wireless technology came out of there.
Um the uh charge coupled devices that
are our cameras came out of there. Uh
they they tried to do video phones and
couldn't get it to work because well
hardware hadn't grown up to it but they
were trying to do it. Um the system of
cells for cell phones came out of not
that building but another building for
Bell Labs. It's it was just a great
place. And so the computer science
people tended to talk to people doing
other things. So I remember when I was
doing simulations,
I was helping somebody uh building a
simulator for some networking stuff. Uh
a lot of early C++ had to do with uh
doing things like what happens when a
network get overloaded? how do we handle
the overload protocols?
And in this particular case, they did a
a good job and they called me back and
um they had a slightly bigger problem.
They wanted to simulate the computer
traffic of Manhattan.
Even then my answer was no. We don't
have the compute power to do that. Uh,
it doesn't matter how good C++ is, the
computers of today can't do it.
>> That back then though, but now now they
probably could, but of course the
computer traffic has become uh much
more. So maybe they can't. I don't know.
I don't have the numbers now. Then I
they gave me the numbers. That was why I
I declined to to to help them because it
was impossible.
>> I saw somewhere when I was doing
research that you you said you had
gotten lunch with Dennis Richie once a
week for like 16 years or something like
that.
>> Um and you know he's uh also a very
legendary name. And I was curious, you
know, if there's anything that you you
learned from him or anything that
impressed you about him that maybe
influenced you or C++.
>> He was a great guy and we talked about a
lot of things. He never said anything uh
rude or or negative about um C++.
Actually, in his Hubble paper, he points
to C++ as the obvious successor to C.
Um, so all of these
C versus C++ language wars are
ridiculous.
Um, they should never have happened and
they certainly didn't happen uh because
well I I knew Dennis. We we were not
fighting. Um I still know Brian Kernan.
I was talking to him this Friday. Um
we're good friends and uh yeah language
walls are are silly. Um Dennis helped me
uh design const for instance for uh C++.
It used to be called read only and write
only but uh the C guys couldn't handle
two words and they were too long. Um so
we we got what we got but that's one
specific thing I remember. Dennis uh
being helpful with uh he was a bit
worried that about
overloading because you had to look at
the
de declarations of functions uh before
you knew what the meaning of a call was.
Um but that's a very eable way of
thinking. It's just happens that it it
works and anybody who writes C today are
using my handiwork essentially all of
the time because the the modern syntax
for function definitions and function
declarations
and the call semantics uh came out of
the early um C++ early classes work of
mine. So when when people start ranting
um they they they should remember that
they're actually doing my using my
handiwork every day. [laughter]
>> You had written these uh uh almost like
historical accountings of the history of
C++ like maybe three really long papers
um I think for some conference I forgot
the exact and so in there there was one
anecdote about Dennis Richie. It was it
was about this this concept where he
proposed uh to the C standard committee
this idea of a fat pointer where it uh
you know also has it it stores its size
as well and you mentioned the C
committee didn't approve and I was
curious if you could like tell that
>> um
so Dennis did see but he didn't take
part in the standards committee and I've
even heard people from the C standards
committees He says, "No, Dennis isn't a
C expert. He's not ever come to
meetings."
Um, very strange attitude, but anyway,
um, we knew the problem about um about
buffer overflow and range errors. And
the obvious solution is to use what
Dennis called a fat pointer which is a
pointer with its number of elements it
points to attached to it. But that's two
words and uh that's probably no that is
why it wasn't used on the early se uh
because then they had 48k of memory and
when when I had this discussion with
Dennis I think we had a whole megabyte
um and when I started with C++ we had
kilobytes and I knew that uh we we were
going to get um get a megabyte and and
we were talking about it and he he
called them fat pointers and today in
C++ they're called span and um the span
came out of uh my work with others on
the C++ core guidelines and we needed
something like that we couldn't provide
the degree of control and safety that uh
we needed so we built span and it came
into the standard a bit later.
But some of these ideas are very old.
>> When you put together really impressive
people like you know the world's
greatest people that you look around and
you see how great the other people are
and even though each individual is great
just the greatness of others can give
people this feeling of imposter syndrome
that's not necessarily founded. Is that
something that you ever felt or saw at
>> Bell? Definitely. Um maybe I still got a
bit of it, but certainly when I came to
Bell Labs and saw the names on the doors
and I'd read the papers and it created
the fields I like to work in. Yeah. I I
thought I have to up my game. I have to
do something uh bigger and better than
what I had imagined. Um also you talk to
them and you learn things. I mean, I
learned a lot over lunch where there's a
bunch of them uh talking about what
they're doing and why they are doing it.
There are some places that that has that
effect on on people and has this density
of talent. Um Cambridge University was
computer science was one of those
places. I learned a lot there and u the
doors were always open. Uh it was sort
of almost a policy uh that we kept the
doors open because how else would people
be able to come and and talk?
>> When we talk about a programming
language and just generally like
language design, if I was to want to
build a programming language today, what
are all the pieces that you'd need to to
build to make a programming language?
Well, that's a relatively easy
question to answer and everybody asks
that question and I think it's a wrong
question. Uh what you need is a problem
that needs a solution. A lot of people
just want to build a language that is
better that at what they are doing now
and what they particularly are doing.
And most of the time that can be done
reasonably well with existing languages.
And
if you build a very specialized language
that's fine. But if we're talking about
more general purpose languages,
uh you you're then building something
that when you want to work with somebody
else, it's not ideal for them. So um I'm
sometimes asked why C++ is so big and uh
complicated
and uh there's two reasons. One is
history. Um I could not build the C++ I
wanted uh back in the 80s. um for a
variety of reasons, partly uh
technology, partly uh computers,
um and partly because I didn't know
enough and I had to learn. So you do the
standard engineering thing, you do the
best you can, then you see what works
and what doesn't work and you try and
fix the problems and then you repeat.
And that's how C++ grew. And so there's
some
leftover things that just gets into the
people's way. Now you have spans. You
very rarely use pointers and you should
certainly not use pointers as resource
handles. Uh that was already built in
with C classes in 79, but people didn't
get it. Um and so there's teaching to do
it. But anyway, uh once you figure out
that you have a problem that require a
new language,
then uh you start looking what there is
and uh you have lots of help, lots of uh
books about analysis and about
um code generation. You have frameworks
like LLVM that most of the modern
languages uses to generate decent code.
So most of the languages that compete
with C++ does it by uh using a C++
infrastructure. It's it's highly
amusing. Um but but anyway, focus on the
problem and don't think you're the only
user. If you think you're the only user,
you build a special purpose programming
language and that's fine. Uh domain
specific languages are great when you
find the right
uh solution to the right problem, but
identify the problem first. Uh in my
case, the problem was I needed high and
low-level facilities
in the same language. Otherwise, I had
to use two languages and I had to have
them communicate uh properly. High level
languages at the time uh tended to uh
use interfaces that took away
performance. Uh quite often they
required garbage collection which is not
very good for device drivers for
instance or for building garbage
collectors. Um so yes identify the
problem and uh try and solve it.
>> Back when you were creating C++ and you
had identified the problem and so then
you went off to build C++ and you know
there's all these pieces right there's
the compiler there's a there's a linker
there's you know in the implementations
of those there's uh like a parser alexer
and you know all those things. uh when
you were building the original thing,
what was the most technically
challenging part to implement?
>> I don't think any part was particularly
challenging. It was more that there was
many parts as you point out. One of the
things I decided that caused trouble uh
later was that I wasn't going to touch
the linker. And it came simply because I
asked around and I realized people were
using about 25 uh different linkers in
in Bell Labs just just in Bell Labs. And
so if I wanted to serve uh my obvious
initial uses, I would have to write
interfaces or modifications to 25
linkers. And nobody wants you to touch
their linker because if you make a
mistake, everything breaks.
So I decided a rule don't mess with the
linker. Later people have messed with
the linkers and made them better for C++
but that was after C++ became a major
issue. Uh the other thing was that there
was many different optimizers.
every
um computer uh from different sources
had a different optimizer and again I
couldn't write u a dozen optimizers.
I mean I'm I'm going to write a language
here right and I can't if I wanted to be
a optimizer specialist for uh deck
computers say um I can become that I
have the background I have the training
but that wasn't what I wanted to do I
wanted to build first a distributed
system and then when my friends and
colleagues started using seu classes um
I wanted to help them uh and they were
doing things like network simulations,
hardware layout,
uh positioning of satellites,
all kinds of interesting stuff. So that
was worth doing. And [snorts] so I
decided that actually there was a common
interface to all these optimizers and uh
code generators. It's called C. So let's
use C as the assembler.
And that worked nicely. C was very good
at the low level was part of the reason
I chose it. So let's use it for the low
level. And I could have hidden C and re
uh created a probably a better
interface. But I decided that uh
I'll just use C have C compatibility.
Uh at the time what I said was that well
we can have Dennis's mistakes which we
know and we can have my mistakes which
we don't know yet. Um so uh we'll take
Dennis's that's u much more manageable
and understandable and I don't have to
teach people how to write a for loop and
things like that. So
that's C compatibility came in that way
partly as an implementation technique
partly uh to get into the culture and uh
tool support and such.
I saw somewhere in in my research that
um you know C++
was used to write some part of uh the
the language tool chain and to me
immediately I have this thought of
there's this chicken and egg problem
because how do you use this language to
build something that it is using itself
h how does that work
>> this is bootstrapping and it's uh it it
was not an unusual ual thing. So I
started with C and in C I wrote a um a
pre-processor that did some of the
fundamental things in uh in in in what
became C++
uh classes and fairly simple inheritance
and overloading and such. And then I
in that I wrote a a simple compiler for
again what was a subset of uh of of C++.
And uh now I can use uh operator
overloading and overloading in general
classes. So I can build a a scope class
that handles look up and naming and
things like that. And then then you work
from there. Um
just writing the next version in the
previous version. You keep keep going
and uh after a couple of years you have
something that became known to the world
as C++. and I wrote a book about it and
a compiler um came out in the world. But
I didn't invent this technique. This was
known as bootstrapping. Um I think I was
taught it as an undergrad that you could
do things like that.
>> Most people they look at C++ and they
think that's an object-oriented
language. And I've heard you say
multiple times that that's not the case
or that's not your immediate thought.
And why is that? Yeah, I I never called
it an object-oriented
uh programming language. If you look at
the C++ programming language, the first
edition, um the closest I come is to say
uh some some some people call these
techniques object- based.
Actually, it's more focused on classes.
It's type oriented, class oriented. uh
it actually supports the techniques of
object orientation very well and it in
particular follows similar's model of uh
defining types defining classes and
defining class hierarchies to uh handle
uh groups of related uh classes but that
was never all it was for instance I do
not want object object oriented complex
numbers. I don't want to say two dot uh
uh something to
uh to to get to uh some parts of uh
numbers. I really want to say uh two two
plus uh zed. Um, and I want that to be
the end up being roughly the same as set
plus two. And um, no dots, no arrows.
Uh, math has developed a notation over
the last 300 years or so. Uh, Decard
was, I think, the first one to to use
this notation and it is very good. Uh,
so I I didn't want everything to to be
object-oriented.
Uh furthermore, I wanted
things that did not require inheritance
that did not require runtime resolution
not to use it. Um so for arithmetic
and for complex numbers and such I
wanted for compatibility.
I mean I was rather keen on what's
called use reuse in those days but I saw
it slightly different from a lot of
researchers. A lot of researchers wanted
to build a language a system that
allowed res um reuse. I wanted to re re
use things that existed. I mean forran
was there uh with some great uh
software. uh C was there with some great
uh system software and actually helped
with with compilers and such and there
was a simpler that was used a fair bit
too. So I wanted to reuse that and I
wanted to make sure that worked and that
meant I couldn't go too far away from
the hardware. I couldn't build uh all of
the things that was considered ideal or
even the things I would consider ideal.
Um this is the real world. This is the
real set of problems you are attacking.
And so you have to respect the
constraints uh that comes with with that
view of the of what you're doing. at the
time that you wrote C++, C was already
there and it had a weaker type system
than what C++ eventually had. And I was
guess your thoughts on, you know, the
trade-offs behind that and why did you
choose to make the typing system
stronger in C++?
>> Because we needed it. Um uh the weakness
in the type system is one of the most
obvious sources of uh errors and it's
certainly one of the sources of um
endless testing and uh debugging. I hate
debugging. I would much rather do
design. And so you can't really have
either design or debugging. Some people
claim they can but they can't. Uh so I
want to move the the arrow over towards
more design uh that helps the debugging
and makes fewer uh mistakes at runtime.
And uh the type system is is one of
them. And uh actually what you get in C
today to a large extent is stronger well
no it is much stronger uh type than it
was in those days and partly because of
C++.
Um also there's things you can't express
unless you have a strong type system. Um
I mentioned overloading before. Uh
overloading is essential for generic
programming. And if you want to write
say a vector of T where T is a parameter
type, you have to have overloading
because you can only operate on T's
providing all the T's have the same
interface
uh for what you need. So you you need
the type system to resolve those things
and that can be resolved at compile
time. So the compiler gets a bit more
complicated probably a bit slower
but you don't do so much debugging. Um
there was a largecale
experiment done in Bell Labs in Chicago
where they had
some groups using C++ switching to C++
and they wanted to know whether they
were more or less uh productive.
And some people claimed that the slower
compilation slowed them down.
And uh somebody simply measured how much
compile time was used uh before after
switching to C++. And they found that
the amount of [snorts]
commulation time of compute power was
roughly identical. that is C++ was
slower but you uh by about a factor of
two at that time but the C people
compiled twice as often.
Um this is just one experiment. the
factor of two is is is just one
experiment but um
I wanted to move towards using more
compile uh compile time resolution still
doing that
>> I mean for every language there's this
um you know dichotomy of having it being
statically typed versus dynamically
typed and C++ is one of the most famous
statically typed languages why did you
choose statically typed language
>> because of the problems I wanted to um
to attack. Um what do you do when you
get a runtime error and
in something like small talk? You go
into the debugger
and that makes a lot of sense if there's
a programmer sitting at a screen uh
getting the error. It doesn't make any
sense if a telephone switch um finds a a
runtime error and then you have to
resolve it. Furthermore, you want
performance and you want small programs
to fit into memories. This is true even
today because as I think 99% of all
computers are embedded systems and they
tend to be uh memory rest constraint
and um again if you do runtime
resolution you need to have enough
information enough data to do the
runtime resolution and I wanted to fit
into small memories. uh small meaning
100 uh
120k 250k 1 megabyte things like that
and I think it's still relevant uh for
for many systems uh you can build a a
camera like that it can still have
several megabytes of memory but uh if
you put in a lot of memory it gets
bigger and it cost more and the battery
um runs out uh quicker. So, we don't do
that. Um phones and cameras and things
like that are still memory constraint.
And um static type languages, languages
optimized for memory consumption are
just better at that, which is why we use
it. We're using it right now. I suspect
that the microphones have uh chips in
them, too. And there's a lot of C++ in
that uh world.
Uh the composition there is C and
assembler.
>> And you mentioned the the research that
was done on the the compile time on you
know if you catch things earlier you
compile less often but maybe it takes
longer. In this case, I I could see a
similar analogy where um you catch
errors way earlier if you have a
statically typed language because the
compiler is yelling at you before you
put together that final thing. Whereas
in dynamically typed language, the
errors may come later. Comparing for a
developer like which one is more time
efficient.
>> I I don't know any solid research on
that, but you can look at it. uh
JavaScript and Pythons are very are very
uh popular and they are um runtime
uh checked and they run much slower. I
mean raw uh Python runs something like
70 times slower than raw C++ and the
reason it's viable is that a lot of key
uh Python libraries are written in C or
C++ to get the performance and so you
get the performance by actually getting
to the point that I was starting out
with you need a highle stuff and you
need the thing that can manipulate
hardware.
uh here they are using two languages but
uh still the same uh needs fundamental
needs
and uh it's easier to uh try out things
in a dynamically uh check language
because you don't have to know enough
about the language. You don't have to
know about type systems and your average
uh web developer or astrophysicist
is not a computer scientist and don't
want to become one. So there's
advantages there. But the problem is
that errors that are found by the type
system in a statically typed language is
found at runtime later. And so as
systems grow
uh the performance problems uh start
furthermore you find it get harder to
write reliable
uh software. uh you need much more unit
testing for instance in a dynamic uh
language because it's um
well
the compiler doesn't do it for you. And
if you want things to guarantee to work
like the telephone switch mustn't crash,
your car mustn't crash, your plane
mustn't crash. You want guarantees and
they're harder to provide in a very
flexible dynamic type system.
>> One thing that I think C++ is uh
infamous for is kind of like memory
safety issues or kind of foot guns that
exist there.
>> I'm so tired of that. Um I haven't had
those problems for years. Um, and
somebody did a a study of
the obvious problems with buffer
overflows and um
people hacking in using that kind of
stuff and uh
almost all of the uh these cases when
people writing C style code or in C
and uh Herb Server has a a talk with
with actual numbers and they they are
quite significant. It's it's sort of
that kind of problems
more than 90% are for people that don't
write modern C++.
They they use raw pointers to pass
things around without
um the number of elements. No fat
pointers, no spans.
um you you have them in C++. You can use
them. You can use uh vectors. We have
hardened libraries. Everybody has
hardened libraries that that does the
runtime checking. Uh Apple has it.
Google has it. Microsoft has it. It's
just not standard till now. C++ 26 has a
hardened option that are standard. uh
and the work I'm doing on profiles will
give you a way of guaranteeing that you
don't do the stupid things.
Um
so anyway, uh fundamentally
theoretically the problem was solved
many years ago and people just do what
they've always done and get the problems
they've always had. And uh that makes me
sad and uh it's one of the things that
makes me work on uh coding guidelines
and on enforced profiles and on
education.
>> I mean education is one way to solve the
problem. Is there a way to get the
compiler to just prevent people from
doing all those risky things?
>> And is that enabled by default in modern
C++ today?
>> No, but it should be. I'm proposing that
for C++ 29. Uh the simpler versions of
that should have been in in in uh C++
26, but there are still a lot of people
even in the C++ standards committee that
are very devoted to uh their old code
and their old ways of doing things. Um
there's people who says you should only
standardize what is common in industry.
But when the bugs are common in
industry, you should do something else.
>> The standards committee is a a topic I
want to talk about actually. It's
interesting. I mean the language is now
run um you know by a democracy and one
question I want to ask you is if it was
a dictatorship so you just had full say
what what language features would be in
that you know maybe a harder to get by
>> f first of all it never was a
dictatorship uh I I never had full
control once you have some users in my
opinion you gain some responsibility for
making sure that they're helped and
their stuff works. You can't keep
breaking the language. That's what
academic language development does. They
they they break to improve all the time
and then they can't maintain a user
population. I didn't actually choose to
have a standards committee. I I chose
responsibility to the commuter to the uh
to the community. But one day um two
guys came in uh representing uh IBM and
HP
and I can't remember if it was Sun or
Deck that was the third thing they
represented but anyway the biggest
computer and software uh suppliers in
the world at the time they come into my
office in it was uh
ah it's 89 n and they say well pian you
want to help us standardize C++ under
ISO rules
and I said no I can't do that I'm still
doing experiments it's still not
complete
so they said no B you don't get it
our
organizations cannot use a language
that's not standardized
they cannot use a language that's owned
by a corporation that we might compete
with and we do sometimes.
Okay, we we we trust you of course but
not your employer.
We compete with them sometimes and you
can get run over by a boss. This uh No,
no, no. We need a standards and we need
a standards committee. So this goes on
for about an hour and they twist my arm.
Ow ow ow. And in the end they said okay
I I I I will uh standardize C++ under
anti- rules uh just like you suggest and
you need the the computer community
needs that and u by the way what's NI
rules for standardization
and um so they told me and we started a
year later but um this this was the way
it came about some very important
important organizations wanted that
standardization.
C was on the track to get standard
standardized
and AT&T being primarily a user of
software was also in favor of
standardization I found out and so they
supported it and the documentation I had
written was bases on it. Actually, I
rewrote the documentation that became
the the ARM, the annotated C++ standards
uh manual that uh gave the definition
the manual of the language and for every
feature some rationale and some way it
could be implemented or was implemented
[snorts]
and that became the the foundation
document for the standardization.
when they were strongarmming you, what
if you had just said no? Like what would
have happened? I think well I think C++
would have faded into becoming an
academic
um
cute uh language that
was loved by some small community and it
would have disappeared out of the
mainstream of uh
of computing. And uh there are people
who say this stronger than I I do. Um
they say that C++ is spread and uses is
that it has a standard. It's not owned
by a corporation. It is one of the
things that sometimes blocks the um the
the the the wannabe C++ killers. I
remember the ads for Java and people
standing up saying we'll kill absolutely
kill C++ in two years. I thought that
was rude. Um and anyway, we have
10 12 times more C++ developers today
than we had when they said it. So, uh
didn't work.
How is it that um C++ and not not
exactly that it's a war but just if we
looked at um adoption you know clearly
C++
gained a lot more adoption than Java yet
I know C or Java had the backing of uh
you know a big company that's putting a
lot of marketing dollars in and C++ was
kind of I I think you've said that it
had almost zero you know next to zero
marketing done for
uh next to zero was $5,000
to be used over three years
and uh son used
much more money on advertising and
marketing uh Java than was ever used in
C++ uh development.
Um and to this day the standards
committee has a problem. government has
no funding
and uh that means that it's hard to do
experiments. It's hard to deploy things
and uh other language communities keep
um sort of stealing uh C++ uh compiler
and tool developers because they're
good. Uh but it's makes it hard to to to
predict how fast we can implement things
today. Last I checked, the C++ standards
committee had 527
members and we work on consensus.
Uh because if you don't have consensus
then you get dialects. Um, we don't want
to have a feature in that's voted in um,
say 60 to uh, 40 or even worse 52 to 48.
No uh, percent. We we we don't do that
and uh, that's painful and tedious and
good.
>> When you say consensus that 100% need to
approve
>> 100% is not uh necessary. We we don't
need unanimity. We need a massive
majority and basically I would like to
see 90%.
And we often do 80% I start to worry.
And what's the lower bound that's coded
into the rules?
>> There's no lower bound coded into the
rules. The rule says that the convenor
or of the ISO committee um determines
what is consensus.
So
pure numbers doesn't say it. Could you
imagine you had
a vote [snorts] 95%
versus 5%.
But the implementers of C++
compiler and standard libraries from
Google, Apple, Microsoft uh and uh
others were all in the 5%. Is that
consensus? I can reassure you that no
convenor would call that consensus.
>> And that makes sense intuitively. I kind
of wonder with democratic decisions
there needs to be objective rules. So
like what if the convenor made the wrong
decision? It happens but
you you can't just have numeric rules.
Uh not everybody cares for the whole
language. Not everybody uh understands
what's going on. You can vote at your
third meeting. So you you might have uh
somebody with a vote that has uh
well eight months of experience with the
standardization and don't understand
standardization and knows only what they
known from their development
organization that they have been part of
which might be a small one. um you you
you need some some judgment and you hope
that the convenor has that judgment. the
convenor uh always uh asks the national
representatives
um I mean the other way of getting a
consensus is that you have a massive
consensus but you have 10 countries that
where the representatives didn't agree
that's not consensus and even when there
looks if there is a
look if everybody body is for, if it's
massive and all of that, there's not a
problem. But if there's a problem, the
convenor
asks the national body heads, he asks
the implementers,
uh, sort of key people that are
necessary for getting the
voted change
uh, into real use. sometimes educators
also uh before they make that decision.
Uh not everybody weighs equally uh once
there's a disagreement. For this podcast
I produced transcripts for every episode
for convenient skimming and I built a
custom tool to automate that. Recently I
noticed in the Barbara Liskoff
transcript my simple speechtoext tool
was getting a lot of things wrong. For
instance, the clue programming language
is spelled all caps clu, not clue. So to
fix this, I used cursor 3, picked the
strongest version of opus 4.7 extra high
and had an agent make a plan to fix
that. And while I was waiting, I figured
I'd trigger a few more agents for code
cleanups and front-end improvements. Um,
it generated a reasonable plan with rich
system diagrams. It applied all the
changes within minutes and worked on the
first try. So if you want to build
something with the flexibility of
sending off a bunch of agents with
frontier models of your choice, you can
go to cursor.com to try out cursor 3.
OpenAI, [snorts]
Enthropic, Cursor, and Verscell all use
this product to make their lives better.
And the problem it solves is when you're
building SAS or an AI product and you
want to sell to other companies, there's
all these requirements you need to meet.
There's SSO, there's SKIM, there's
arbback, there's audit logs. These are
all things that take time to integrate
but aren't the main focus of your app.
Work OS is an API layer that lets you
meet all of these requirements in just a
few lines of code. So, let's say you
have a new SAS product and you want to
sell to other companies. Work OS will
solve all of these critical feature gaps
for you. You can check them out at
workos.com to learn more and get
started. and I appreciate them for
supporting my work and sponsoring this
podcast.
>> About the standards committee, I I saw
in some of your writing, you said um one
of the most negatively received ideas
you'd ever presented was uh auto. And I
know auto eventually made its way in
there, but what's the story behind why
it was so, you know, negatively received
at that time?
>> It was just unusual. people thought was
weakening the type system.
And uh also it opens the door to fairly
general generic programming that is not
heavily uh syntax based. And auto is the
beginning of concepts which is the um
ability to put constraints on uh generic
code. And auto is just the simplest
constraint. It must be a type as opposed
to a say a value seven. [snorts]
And uh maybe I didn't explain this well
enough uh and there's a variety of
backgrounds and in the committee and
maybe they they didn't know languages of
the uh generic types uh ML hasll things
like that. So it it was it was horrible
uh
um so anyway we still got it um because
we we needed something like that but it
wasn't enough. I have looked at
industrial software and problems with
overuse of auto. You should only use
auto when you have an idea about what is
needed there. It's good in generic code
where there's uh you you you go and
eventually you check the the type is
correct that auto has resolved to
something that supports the uh
operations that you're going to do on it
and that's what concept formalizes but
it was always checked at the end and I
noticed a group of people that was
overusing auto in a
actually in a framework for um
networking.
And they were saying that they were
being slowed down, not so much with
bugs, but they had to look up the
functions being called to see what that
auto could possibly bind to.
And then they had to put in comments
that says what the the um what the auto
uh was meant. So you you have auto and
the comment says uh must be an input
channel.
Now you simply define input channel and
then instead of saying auto you say
input channel auto
fine that's what the system is uh my
design of that simply said that auto is
the simplest concept and you should
simply only set input channel uh C
equals blah blah blah but anyway the the
committee wanted a an indicator that
this was going on.
Oh, well,
>> I saw another anecdote in kind of the
standards committee being heated at some
times. You mentioned there's this thing
about shuttle diplomacy between two
corners of the room because I think it
was IBM and Intel. They both needed
different support.
>> That's right.
>> What's the story behind that? And I was
actually talking to Brian Mcnite who
were the IBM rep at the time and it was
last week and we were we were discussing
some of the things that was happening
then. So it it's still remembered. So
basically IBM was doing the uh what's
that architecture called? Uh
>> uh power PC. Power PC and um
>> the X86
>> and the Intel was doing well Intel and
they have different models of the
underlying hardware especially uh
coordination with the uh caches and
things like that. And basically
yeah and uh the guy representing Intel
wasn't actually an Intel guy. that was
uh uh he he he and any anyway
also a good guy. I use some of his
slides in my presentations. It's uh so I
knew these guys but they were totally
deadlocked. I mean this these are
massive again massive organizations with
massive amounts of code out there and um
uh
[sighs]
basically
some things could be done but
the the IBM guy Brian
said that they had a lot of software
mostly in the lowest level even down in
the the microode uh that was relying on
the way they have done it and the people
who had done it had left the company.
They they was done a long time ago and
they just couldn't rewrite all of that
code and get it right even if the intel
guys was right.
Okay. And the intel guys had similar uh
arguments and similar uh points. This is
better. We are using it. And so I was
shuffling. They were definitely they
were in different corners of a large
room. And so I go up to the Intel guy,
um, the guy representing Intel here and
what's the problem here? Tell him tell
me about it. Explain it. I go down,
explain he's saying this. They say,
"Well, there's this, this, this." And I
go back again. And I spent a couple of
hours literally doing shuttle diplomacy,
walking from one corner of the room to
the other. And um we we reached an
agreement and that's in uh C++ 11.
And a couple of years later they both uh
agreed that they were now using a
combination of what they had before and
what the other guys brought in. So we
they actually the result was uh was
improvement
cross-pollination.
>> That's funny. Why did you have to do
shuttle diplomacy? Why not just a group
conversation with
>> Because they've been trying that for
days and probably for meetings before
that and it didn't work.
So I I guess I was just translating and
asking questions.
I mean those were experts. I don't
consider myself expert at that level. Um
I mean I've done hardware. I've done
microode. So I'm I'm not an amateur, but
but these guys are really good. Um,
[snorts]
so the the the the IBM guy is now the
guy doing most of the synchronization
under Linux.
We're we're still using his stuff uh
today. He has a C version of it so he
can get it into the but it's a bottom of
the uh Linux kernel. When I was reading
your writing in these papers, there's
this part where it seems like in 1995,
you had this idea to introduce uh some
form of automatic garbage collection
into C++. And that kind of surprised me
because when I when I think about C++,
my one of my immediate thoughts is no
garbage collector. We're going to man
manually or you know manage the memory
ourselves. How how would that even work?
Um
there's two things there. One, I wanted
to automate
resource management in general, not just
garbage and not just memory. And uh for
that you have constructors, destructors
and the techniques that was later later
known as uh our AI resource acquisition
is initialization
which is probably my worst naming ever.
But um I was busy at the time. Um so
in the standards committee those people
that insisted that we needed to be able
to do garbage collection
and there was garbage collectors out uh
there. Oh that was Hans Berm. He was the
one that representing the internal model
of stuff. He he has a conservative
garbage collector still used today and
we thought we needed an interface so
that uh it could be standard how you
used such a garbage collector
and so basically I was listening to the
users expert users and they thought it
was necessary. I thought that support
for
memory management, resource management
was important. I've thought that from
the beginning. I didn't think garbage
collection was appropriate for a lot of
what I was doing, but certainly um
automating
uh the management was ideal.
And so after a long set of discussions
we found an interface that people agreed
on and uh we put it into C++ 11. And
what we found was over the next 10
years,
the amount of usage of garbage
collection decreased
as um our AI, the uh resource management
that had been there all the time got
more and better understood and was used
more.
Furthermore, the people who still used
the garbage collectors didn't use the
standard interface because they had
figured out ways of doing it better. And
so today, there are still a few people
doing garbage collection, but it's not
part of the standard.
>> How does that work? Is it kind of like a
wrapper around the uh memory allocation
methods?
>> Yeah.
>> Okay. you you have you have a a
different implementation of
uh new or maloc or operator new or
whatever it is you're using at your
lowest level and then um delete becomes
something slightly different too.
there's this cautionary tale in the C++
community about uh this ship Vasa and I
was kind of curious like why that's
popular and
>> oh um
we had a meeting in Stockholm at some
point and they have a wonderful ship
that if you ever get to Stockholm you
should see the Vasa. It's a battleship
from the 1600s. There's a story to that
and that's the one I tell people. Um
the king was building was was ordering
built a battleship that should be the
best and most beautiful battleship
around. Uh it was going to be a good
fighting battleship and it was going to
be used for diplomatic uh visits. So it
should be beautiful. [snorts]
And uh they laid down the keel and they
started building it. And then they heard
that a likely opponent was building
battleships with two gun decks.
And this was an then old-fashioned
battleship with only one gun deck. And
if you put a two gun a one gun deck
battleship next to a two gun deck
battleship, the highly predictable
result is a lot of holes in the one um
gun deck battleship and it it's gone.
So the king orders that this ship should
now have two gun decks
and um they've already started building
it.
So they add another Glend, they add
cannons up there. And the king also
wants now the ship is bigger. They want
more statues and beautiful things. So it
becomes a bit topheavy.
And uh rumor has it I've never checked
this rumor so it might be wrong. Uh is
that the ship designer committed suicide
uh out of horror. Um I also a thing that
I don't believe is just a rumor was when
they was built they tested it for
stability. And the way you test a st a
[snorts]
and ship like that for stability is you
take the whole crew and you run them
from one side to the other back forth
get harmonic uh stair and if you can do
that 14 times then uh it'll stand up to
the Baltic and the North Sea.
Rumor has it actually as I said I think
it's a fact um that they did it seven
times and then they stopped because it
looked dangerous.
So um
this was
I think. Um, the ship gets finished. Uh,
it's sailing out. The most wonderful
ship you've ever seen. It's sailing out
in uh Stockholm Harbor. Trumpets, uh,
blaring flags flying, uh, families of
crews on board, the whole thing. It gets
halfway across the, uh, harbor, a gust
of wind comes, it kills the war, and
it's gone. And it ends down in some
place where there's not much um
much oxygen. So it was well preserved
and they fished it up again. Uh and you
can see it. And so I tell this story to
the standards committee and I point out
there's something they did wrong. They
built more features on top without
improving the foundation.
always improve the foundation to make
sure that it's just not a a random set
of features that you have added because
that's complexity.
Furthermore,
do not um compromise your testing.
That's really dangerous. And
furthermore, uh you you've all noticed
when your high bosses say something
should be done and the high bosses don't
always know what's right. Uh sometimes
the professional thing is to say no, we
are not doing this. We have to take it
easy. If they had said, okay, we'll
build a one uh gun battleship. We'll
just not call it the Vasa. Call it
something neutral. And then next year
you can have a battleship that's been
designed from the bottom up to be a two
gun battleship. You wouldn't have any
problems with that. But the high
management, meaning the king who was in
Poland at the time, so he couldn't even
see it, says, "Nope, must be delivered
on time." And so they delivered
something on time that just couldn't do
the job.
But go see the ship. It's great.
>> At some point uh someone demonstrated
that the C++ template instantiation
mechanism was turning complete. So you
know what the compiler is going to do to
kind of pre-process that C++ program can
actually be used for computation just uh
and I was just trying to understand h
how is that possible like how it it was
mentioned something about he uh
calculated prime numbers at compile
time. How does that work?
>> Well that's I mean the prime number
thing was was just a a curiosity. it uh
used the error messages to report the
result. But um when you build something
uh you can get Turing completeness um
you you you need some form of uh iterate
or recurse and you need a um [snorts] a
comparison and that's about it. then you
can get true to incompleteness and the
at least some of the theoreticians says
we can't do that it'll run forever and
um the guy who uh
who came up with with the first example
of this uh actually thought I should
prohibit it somehow I should ban it and
my reaction was this looks useful Great.
And uh I think I was right. Furthermore,
nothing runs forever. If you have a
Turing machine, you have the tape
and the tape has to be infinite.
So if if you imagine building a real
cheing machine the way Turing designed
it, you have to have a bunch of navies
building track all the time when it gets
out there. Of course, we don't do that.
The point is that the compiler will run
out of resources long before we get into
real problems. Machines are finite
and so the problem does
doesn't become real in in unless there's
bugs and the bugs get caught guaranteed.
So not a problem. What happened though
was that people were misusing
templates to do simple calculations.
like prime numbers or your trust is yeah
your sustenance is se or u calculating
factorials and such and it's so awful
and it's so expensive and it uses up so
much memory that it becomes a problem so
that was why I and Gabidas re uh built
constexer which basically says you can
calculate perfectly ordinary code at
compile time and it is much simpler,
much more what we're used to and much
faster to compile uh and giving usually
much faster code and um you have that
today and you have constant value if you
want to guarantee that this is done
[snorts]
and uh so that takes care of the obvious
misuses of the idea of uh templates
being during complete it turns them into
ordinary functions.
>> Generally with programming languages
there's this um you know high level
intuition that the closer to the machine
you are the higher the performance is
and um you know I I tend to see C as
closer to the machine than C++ for
instance. Um no that's not the case.
>> It's not the case. It's not as good as
compile time calculation at C++ is. And
anyway, we have exactly the same machine
model because uh um C borrowed the C++
11 machine model. Um so if you write the
same code in both languages, it's you
get the same result except uh the C++
compilers can do more at compile time.
And so C++ runs as fast or faster than C
in most cases. There's more information
if if uh if you give a optimizer more
information, it can do a better job.
>> Ah, okay. Yeah, because that was what I
was going to ask you was you had said
somewhere that C++ can be more
performant than C, but I tend to think
that more abstraction costs you
something. But
>> it's compiled away. This is why I talk
about zero overhead abstraction and
people are beginning to take me to task
for that because that's underestimating
the uh and understating the ability of
the C++ compiler. We can do negative
overhead uh abstraction.
>> What if I was really good at writing
assembly and I had all the time in the
world to write it. Could that how about
how does that compare? If you are very
smart and you have infinite time, uh you
can do better.
Um by and large we are not as smart as
the um optimizers anymore and we don't
have infinite time.
So if we are uh smart enough, we can
only do a small piece of code. And now
um the question is did we get enough
time to use our smarts.
Uh this is even starting to affect
uh clever code.
I gave a talk to uh Slack last year
which is a group of uh very performant
uh interested people from the finance
industry
and my title was don't be clever.
Actually the written title was don't be
too clever but I can't pronounce
parenthesis.
Um and I got out alive.
Um, and my main point was that C++ is
good enough
for uh more than 98% of your code. So if
you want time to be clever,
you use these techniques and I showed
modern C++
and that way you get time so you can do
all the clever optimizations. The
problem is clever optimizations these
days tend to be machine dependent. That
is if you get a new
computer or if you get a new version of
the compiler, you might actually have
pessimized your code. I've seen this
repeatedly ever since the uh the 80s. uh
and there there there's people who does
nothing but uh u using different
optimizations on the next generation
hardware
and u my standard techniques for um for
for improving things actually is to
first throw away the clever stuff
and then see if you run faster or
slower. Usually you run faster because
clever stuff tends and at least 1990s
story style clever stuff which is
there's a lot of it still today because
the techniques uh carry on in people's
heads and uh some of the code remains uh
tend to use a right nest of pointers
and that uh gives the compilers and
optimizers problems.
They also sometimes use uh more
allocations
which is not good. You want to minimize
memory access. You want to maximize uh
your cache performance and things like
that. And compilers are getting very
good at that. And I have seen th this
kind of thinking. I wrote a paper about
it together with a friend of mine in
Spain doing flu fluid dynamics and uh uh
we we we threw away uh the clever stuff
for a uh
actually a performance uh test suite
example. So it was not toy and we got
only 20% improvement
by reducing the code to about 80% of
what it was before and so some people
didn't think that was significant. I
thought it was significant proof that
the technique was appropriate. You apply
optimizations only when you need them.
Kuth says don't do premature
optimization but he also pointed out
that two to 3% is where you uh where you
should optimize which is exactly the
number I'm using
and so first build the stuff using high
level facilities
see if it's good enough and if it isn't
uh and you have to time it you don't
guess you time uh then you uh up then
you figure out where the time is spent
and then you optimize that
but a lot of the time you don't need to
go to that stage it's it's fast enough
>> I see so when you say cleverness here
it's um like human level a manual
management to ek out performance
>> yes
>> and you're saying that actually if you
don't do that the compile you're giving
the compiler more to optimize and it can
do a good job
>> and it's much much better than it used
to
code that was cleverly and correctly
optimized in the 1990s
are often pessimized today
because machine architectures have
changed
and the compilers have improved. When I
look at the industry today, um more and
more of code is being written by
machines than humans. And I I feel like
a lot of programming language design is
thinking about how do you make it u
amendable to humans solving problems and
writing the code. And I'm curious if you
have any thoughts on if you think
programming language design will change
if more and more of the code is written
by you know models and machines. I
think that in the field I'm mostly
interested in,
code will still be written by humans
and they will use abstraction.
The examples I've seen of attempts for
AI to generate code in this domain
uh has not been successful.
it uh they generate more bugs, more
security holes. They have uh bloated
code which pessimize again because you
use more memory
and um it's hard to validate
and the senior developers that would be
needed to validate it um I've seen some
of them starting to retire because they
don't want to deal with the validation
of something that changes every time you
make a change in your code in your
prompts.
And furthermore, a lot of the things I
think about um there's regulatory
bodies, there's validation. You have to
be able to validate what you changed
when you make a change. And the AIS the
the tools change the uh even if you make
a slight different prompt, the uh a lot
of the code will change and you have to
now check it again.
all of the code that was generated and
know there's more code generated than if
it was written by humans. And when a
human make a change, it it'll make a
change that's localized and you can look
for the effects of that localized
change. If an AI writes it, uh it uh it
you don't actually know where it's
changed. You have to try and figure that
out. So if you're doing something that
has been done many times before, you
write a standard web app, uh what you
say is correct. Um also AI is not
useless. That's not what I'm saying. It
can be used to write uh documentation.
Again, it has to be humanly validated,
but it helps write uh things. It's good
at text.
It's not
at least now good at
um
safety critical performance critical uh
code. Now
let's say that 70 or 80% of the code of
the world's code doesn't fit that
pattern but it's the that 10 20% of the
code that I'm interested in and there
it's not there and I don't see it coming
with the LLM model. Furthermore, ILM
when fed with training data
has to be trained with old code.
And my job as I see it is to make sure
people write new things and use new
techniques that are improvement over the
old code. So I find that LLM based code
is imitating old code and getting old
performance and old bugs.
Uh again maybe you can improve that. I
hear rumors of Biana apps being written.
Uh that's fed my uh writings, but even
that is problematic because I'm not
saying exactly the same as I did 20
years ago. But anyway, we we'll we'll
see. Um
also even Dystra was looking into the
possibility and he claimed that um the
idea of having natural languages being
the programming language was idiotic. He
is less polite than I am. And um I think
that a language like English is very
flexible and what we say is often very
ambiguous. We need a programming
language that's precise that's that's
engineering that's math. It's not
English.
And for that code that is uh performance
or safety critical I imagine there will
be some uh group of people that is using
uh LLM for that and I guess based off
what you're saying is the intuition that
you would foresee more breakages and
bugs and uh you know because it's not
valid
>> and the people that are really good at
that kind of stuff uh tend to to not
want to spend all their time validating.
Another problem is that they want to
eliminate
junior programmers because there's lots
of them. But if you do that, where do
you get the senior programmers from?
We will see. I mean, you can ask me the
same question again in 10 years and
there will be more knowledge and uh
undoubtedly some of what I said will not
be correct and my guess is some of what
I say will be correct in 10 years. I'm
always told by AI uh proponents that
uh either the problem has already been
solved or it'll be solved in the next
release.
But I I hear anthropic 4.7 is having
more problems than 4.6
uh for reasons I don't understand. But
the the idea that the next version will
solve the problem uh is is always a a
dangerous assumption. Furthermore,
it's getting more and more expensive. If
you have to build a hundred million uh
dollar um
center and use and run the electricity
for it, how many junior developers uh
does it take to be cheaper?
um they they're starting to uh need
money. It's it's not un problematic and
I'm in a sub field where it is probably
more problematic than most.
One thing I saw in in a profile that you
did is they asked you what keeps you
going on C++ or what motivates you and
you said one is the fun of kind of
building the the future and the second
thing was the obligation to make sure
C++ moves forward and like when you
started C++ I can't imagine you knew
that you were embarking on a journey for
decades and so
>> not not decades But I knew it was a
longer journey because I knew I couldn't
build the language I wanted. I could
build a a subset of it. And there was
two reasons for that. One was well, I
was a I was a team that did it. Um
secondly, um so lack of resources, lack
of time, and secondly, I didn't have the
input needed to make sure that what I
designed was right. And so we have the
engineering issue. Build what you can,
see what works, improve it. And so I
knew I was getting into something like
that. I knew I was building a language
meant to evolve. And meant to evolve
means that you make certain decisions in
um knowing that that is different. For
instance, I that's one reason C++ wasn't
just a uh object-oriented programming
language because I could see in the
world that there was things that didn't
seem to fit that paradigm.
And so I I knew we would evolve. The
other half of that answer to that
question, what keeps me going is
applications.
It's really nice to see interesting uses
and in such. So I was at JPL and uh I
talked to the people was doing the Mars
rovers. That's cool stuff. I've been to
J uh I've been to CERN. I'm going to
CERN this summer to see how you do high
energy physics. I don't know anything
about high energy physics. Well,
probably more than the average, but but
nowhere near being a physicist. And so
you can go there and see they do
interesting things and there's things
that surprise you. So I was talking to a
guy in CERN some years ago and
[clears throat] his job was to open and
close doors.
These doors weigh a couple of tons and
are made of lead and they move across to
close off an area to protect against
radiation or something like that. I
don't know the details, but the point is
he has to start up this door, which is
not too hard. You have engines, but then
you have to make sure you stop it
because when you have a couple of tons
uh this wide going into a wall, it will
not stop normally. Uh you have to write
and the code for that was was
interesting. I learned something and uh
I still travel around and uh talk to
people and see what C++ is being used
for and what it can be used for and what
it can't be used for. Just learning and
learning is fun.
>> There's a a few quotes that you have
which I thought would be interesting
kind of if you could just give some
context behind them. Well, one of the
quotes is C makes it easy to shoot
yourself in the foot. C++ makes it
harder, but when you do it, it blows
your whole leg off.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I I um somebody asked a
question at a talk I was given in uh
Boston back in the 80s and I shot that
one back. Well, not not not thinking. Um
but it's a good quote and it's correct.
Um,
Arnold Penes
got in the Nobel Prize in physics, so
he's not a nobody, was one trying to
explain to a large group of uh, Bell
Labs managers about C++.
And he says, you can't have a power tool
without knowing how to use it. So if you
have a saw, you saw like this. If you
have a power saw and you try and do
that, it'll bounce
and you will have to be very lucky not
to get hurt.
Notice it's roughly the same story.
Uh and so what is behind that is if you
get a power tool and you misuse it, you
will get more uh problems. Get a car
that accelerate faster and it can wrap
you around the tree uh in a way a
old-fashioned slow accelerating car
can't. It's fundamental to having power
tools.
>> You also have this other great quote.
It's um nobody should call themselves a
professional if they only know one
language. I obviously you'd recommend
people learn C++, but if they had to
know a second or a third language for
the sake of you know being a better
engineer or programmer, what would you
recommend?
>> Yeah. And uh if you've heard if you've
seen that interview, you'll know I
waffle on that deliberately.
uh it is not so much which other
languages you know but that you get a
set of ideas that are embedded in those
languages. So what you should do is to
learn languages that are different from
yours
and um I'm not too
fuzzy about which languages they are. I
think I said uh learn learn a scripting
language today that would be Python or
JavaScript. Uh then I guess it was Unix
shell or something like that. Um have a
look at a functional language uh ML or
hasll would be obvious uh solutions or
just pick something
different. The point is that you mustn't
get stuck with just what's in your
language. It It's like it's not good for
you to be monogl
you you know what you call somebody who
knows three languages triilingual who
knows two languages bilingual
uh one language American [laughter]
is a a very popular joke at least
outside America.
Um, and it's the same idea with
programming languages, but it's more
important with programming languages, I
think. Um, because uh you you're you're
building things and you shouldn't you
you should broaden your mind uh with
ideas and techniques.
>> Another quote is people people who think
they know everything really annoy those
of us who know we don't. And I was
curious the context behind that or your
thoughts on
>> Well, that's I mean that's that's very
simple. It's there's so many people who
who who think there simple solutions to
just about everything in the world. Uh
in this context they they'll come and
tell me how how much simpler C++ could
be. And this is true. Um if you only
want to do one thing usually the one
they have in mind you can make a much
simp simpler language but
this is like uh if we throw away this
part of C++ it will be much simpler
nicer usually they want to throw away
things like C. So but then you annoy a
few million people
and you don't actually succeed because
they'll stick to the old stuff. So um
it's a it's a way of expressing my
frustration with people who
oversimplify.
Uh people think they can program without
being learning to program. Uh they think
they can be engineers without learning
engineering. They think they can be
politicians without knowing how to run a
company or a country. Um it's it's
oversimplification annoys me and I
probably shouldn't express annoyance. I
very rarely do but uh in this particular
case it my my frustration showed.
>> Yeah. I think I saw somewhere kind of in
response to C++ being difficult for some
people people who have the perspective
of you know programming should be
approachable and you know anyone can
learn programming. And I think you you
expressed the opinion that C++ is not
necessarily for everyone. It's for
serious programmers.
>> Yeah. I mean uh the the first
line of the C++ programming language uh
version one first edition was uh C++ is
designed to make life more pleasant for
the serious programmer and I took away
the first version which was professional
because I saw amateurs that was really
really good. So a serious programmer is
probably programming for somebody else.
If you program for yourself, it doesn't
matter. It's your it's it's you. Uh and
that's your problem. If you do it for
your friends, you can lose friends. If
you build something for a million
people, you can do harm in the world.
And so that's what it's for. Um
I uh I mean Gildolf and Russen built um
built Python with the explicit aim of
allowing many people or even or
everybody to program and he succeeded.
I designed C++ to be a really good tool
for serious programmers, for engineers
and mathematicians and such and I
succeeded too.
Um, it's just not the same problem.
Remember where we started? I said the
problem look at the problem and then
learn from uh what worked and what
doesn't. Looking back on C++ and the
whole journey, is there any part where
you think oh that that was a mistake or
something that you learned from in the
design?
>> Many many uh times I learned something.
Um
I think most of the things never made it
into C++.
That is that's what you have experiments
for.
And that's what you have initial uses
I think I got the major part of the
language right
and I think I could improve every single
detail.
But
stability, compatibility
is essential.
If you make an insignificant change, it
will annoy a few people and it wouldn't
matter. If you make a significant
change, you will annoy a lot of people
and it will not work because uh say a
million people will stick to the old
way.
So, um I I try to
grow the language without breaking it.
Um I have this thing that happens again
and again. and I explain it. People come
up and say to me C++ is too complicated.
Yeah. Um you you you must simplify it.
And I need these two features. I need
them yesterday. You must when you're
doing this. Give me these two features.
Yes.
And whatever you do, don't break my
code. I have a million lines of it.
That doesn't work. That's impossible.
And so that is why I'm working on coding
guidelines and on profiles which is
enforced guidelines. That way you can
design a profile that ensures that you
can use the libraries that you need and
ensure that you don't misuse the
features that are
unnecessary. and dangerous in your
field. for anyone who wants to um you
know learn C++ I think a common question
is like what is the you know top
technical book recommendation that you
would have
learn modern C++
there's a book I wrote when I was
teaching undergrads this this is
accidental I didn't mean it to be there
but anyway this is a second edition of
uh programming principles and practice
using C++ this is a big fat book um
written for undergrads. The third
edition is not as thick because the
language has improved and uh I can
actually um get the ideas across uh
better with less text. Um but use the
latest uh C++ learn the modern way
first. Don't start learning all the bad
ways of writing C as the starter. And a
lot of courses still says you learn C
first. So you learn some issues maloc
and uh pointers and uh then
later you can learn how to use a vector
on a string and not have the problems.
But
yeah, profiles are there
to be able to have compiler and static
analyzer support for that kind of
thinking.
And educators are asking for something
like that too. A lot of people think the
profile simply is to deal with memory
safety and performance. No, it it has to
give people a better tool uh both for
learning and for doing specific kinds of
work.
>> And then last question for you is if you
could go back to the beginning of your
career and give yourself some advice,
what would you say?
>> Oh dear. Yeah, that's a time machine
question. I I sometimes set that for uh
my students.
Uh you have a time machine. Go back and
uh give Dennis some advice and uh once
you've done that uh uh step 10 years uh
for forward and give me some advice.
It's a it's a good exercise. I usually I
usually get some really good stories out
of it, some suggestions.
Um,
I think
a lot of
I I I tried to avoid the two-way
conversions in of the built-in types and
C.
I should have fought harder for that. I
tried but uh was stopped by the people
in in in Bell Labs. Um and these were
more experienced people than me and
such. Now I I should have should have
gone further there. Furthermore, I
should have delayed the release of C++
till I could have something template
like so I could do a better uh standard
library.
um it wouldn't have been good enough,
but it would have gotten people into the
habit of of using a standard. Everybody
was building standard libraries and we
got saved by uh Alex Stefanov with the
STL. Uh but that was that was real luck
because I made a mistake in in not
delaying till I could have built a a a
good vector and uh class hierarchy. uh
stuff.
And then finally,
if I'd known what I know now about
standards committees and bloated
bureaucracies and we have more subgroups
now than we had members to start out
with, I would have tried very hard to
set up a
um some kind of
steering group so that people could make
suggestions. But
we wouldn't have a vote with say 500
people. We would have suggestions from a
community of 500 people and we would
have maybe a group of five or six people
uh with vast experience and cared for
the whole language who made the
decisions based on what was proposed.
Something like that. But I did not have
the experience or the knowledge to make
such a suggestion.
Uh notice that I did not mention tools.
C++ has a weakness in tools
and that was because it grew up early in
a time with limited tools, limited uh
compute power, limited memory. So I
couldn't have done it. One constraint on
the exercise I give to the uh students
for time machines is try and make sure
that it would be possible to follow your
advice.
And uh if I just said I want this then a
lot of the things couldn't be done till
uh 20 years later and therefore would
never have happened. There's a lot of
languages designed to be perfect
uh for the future uh computers and the
future programmers. Most of them die
because by the time 10 years later they
get the language, the world has changed
>> on that first one. I imagine that would
have been really tough to do because the
the Bell Labs people were so senior.
>> I I failed. I tried. Um, but it's it's
obvious that you don't want narrowing
conversions. I even wrote a paper about
how to get rid of them uh today in a
library
uh last year. But it is a fundamental
flaw in the type system of C and C++.
And it came because they needed they
being people like Dennis Richie and the
Unix team and so they needed to be able
to handle both integers and floating
point and they didn't think of explicit
type conversion and they thought
explicit type conversion was too clunky.
They didn't actually get casts till
about 5 years after they got floating
point integers. And of course you have
to be able to turn a floating point into
an integer, right? And so that you get
implicit conversions whenever you can.
Also things like integers into
characters
uh problematic. But since you are
writing fundamental software, you didn't
want to write something
complicated and you didn't want to have
runtime checking. You couldn't afford
that.
And uh well so it was established uh
long before I came and my my attempts to
to deal with that failed.
>> It sounds like it wasn't for no reason.
It um you know saves resources maybe are
very limited.
>> They didn't have the resources to to
deal with it. They built lint the static
cheer to deal with some of it and uh
small machines. Another thing was that
that group of programmers was
significantly smarter and significantly
more experienced than the average
developer today. We have the law of
large numbers.
uh I think the last num the latest
estimate I've seen on the number of
software developers in the world is 47
million
and at that time with Unix the number of
uh programmers
probably was a few dozen and the ones
that didn't have a PhD in uh from a good
university were geniuses.
it's easier to get a PhD and being a
genius. And so they were for a different
set of problems with a different set of
machines and a different set of people.
Boy, it was a pain and still is.
>> Awesome. Well, thank you so much for
your time, professor. I really
appreciate it.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Hey, thank you for watching this
podcast. If you liked it and you want to
see the show grow, please support with a
comment or a like. Also, if you have any
recommendations for people you want me
to bring on, please drop a comment.
Guests like Barbara Liskoff, Mike
Stonereaker, Mark Brooker, these were
all people that I brought on because
someone left a comment. On another note,
aside from the podcast, I'm working on
building the ergonomic keyboard that I
wish existed. Here's a glance at the
prototype. It's a split keyboard, so
there's two sides. Um, this is in the
case, but yeah, we launched on
Kickstarter and we hit our goal within 8
hours of launching. I really appreciate
it if you were one of the people who
grabbed one of the early units. Um,
we're now working on the long journey of
building the tooling now and so if you
still want to pick one up, I've left the
late pledges open on Kickstarter, so you
can grab one there. I'll put a link in
the description. Thank you again for
watching the podcast and I'll see you in
the next